

Systems Development Engineer specializing **AWS** technologies and **Microsoft Windows Server** environments. Experienced with all stages of the **DevOps** cycle for dynamic automation-based projects on AWS cloud. Well-versed in programming languages including **Windows PowerShell**, **Bash** and **Python**. Strong background in managing organization wide projects and documentation.

SOUMYAJYOTI BISWAS

- **4** +91-7032229423
- soumyajyoti@outlook.com
- 9 540, Jawpur Road Panchanantala, Kolkata West Bengal, 700074, India
- in LinkedIn/SoumyajyotiBiswas
- Github/SoumyajyotiBiswas
- Dev.To/SoumyajyotiBiswas

Skill Highlights

- Windows PowerShell
- Bash
- Python
- Operating Systems: Microsoft Windows Server, Linux, Unix.
- AWS Compute Services: EC2, Lambda, Image Builder.
- AWS Analytics Services: Quicksight.
- AWS Application Integration Services: SNS, SES, EventBridge, SWF, Step Functions.
- AWS Cost Management Services: Cost Explorer.
- AWS Database Services: DynamoDB, AWS RDS.

Experience

06/2021 to present

Systems Development Engineer – Finance Automation, Amazon Development Center, India

- Responsible for writing, deploying and maintaining code to provide cost savings of >\$150K/month in AWS resource billings across teams.
- Responsible for proposing concepts to maintain >100 AWS accounts with standard security baselines.
- Responsible for building, automating and maintaining systems processing billions of dollars in transactions.
- Responsible for building scalable, and highly available infrastructure in AWS cloud.
- Work with a diverse customer base to understand requirements, priorities and processes.
- Work with 3rd party application providers to integrate their infrastructure into Amazon environment.
- Develop project concepts, maintain optimal workflow and technical document writing.
- Work with senior developers to manage large, complex design projects for customers.
- Attend and remediate critical severity incidents to meet service level agreements, and provide incident root cause analysis and remediation steps.
- Participate in hiring events, and mentor onboarding candidates.

03/2018 to 06/2021

Systems Development Engineer – AWS WorkSpaces, Amazon Web Services, Bellevue, USA

- Responsible for designing, writing, testing, and deploying code to provision and maintain agents deployed on Microsoft Windows OS based AWS WorkSpaces for <u>WorkSpaces</u> Streaming Protocol.
- Responsible for designing, writing, testing and deploying code to provision and maintain agents deployed on Microsoft Windows OS based AWS WorkSpaces allowing web browserbased connections to WorkSpaces.
- Work with global customers across all AWS regions to understand business requirements and translate them to technological features and enhancements for the product.

- AWS Developer Tools: Code Builder, Code Commit, Code Pipeline, Code Deploy, CloudShell, Cloud9.
- AWS End User Computing Services: WorkSpaces.
- AWS Management and Governance Services: Auto Scaling, CloudFormation, CloudWatch, CloudTrail, Compute Optimizer, Trusted Advisor, Config, Systems Manager.
- AWS Networking Services: VPC, Route53, CloudFront.
- AWS Security Services: IAM, Directory Services, Guard Duty, KMS, Secrets Manager.
- AWS Storage Services: S3, EBS, FSx, EFS, Storage Gateway.
- Microsoft Windows Server
- Microsoft Active Directory
- Git & GitHub

Certifications

- CCNA (expired) [License 414644171421GKCI July 2013 to July 2017].
- MCPS (expired) [Microsoft License E724-4234 February 2014 to 2017].
- Certified Cisco Systems
 Instructor (expired), January
 2014 Score: Passed, partnered
 with NIIT under instructor:
 Prithvi Narayan.
- ITILv3 (expired), EXIN License 5201537 November 2014.

Recognitions

- Most valuable professional, Amazon WorkSpaces, AWS.
- Finance Technology Individual Recognition, Amazon Dev Center, India (x2).
- Extra Mile, Capgemini.

Education

⊗ B-TECH E.C.E, M.S.I.T, 2013.

Experience

- Work as Microsoft Windows subject matter expert, and find solutions to complex problems unique to customer environments.
- Attend and remediate critical severity incidents to meet service level agreements, and provide incident root cause analysis and remediation steps.
- Work with global customer engagement teams to write standard operating procedures, and support knowledge documents.
- Work with security teams to remediate any vulnerabilities in automation code.
- Work with technical documentation writers to enhance content related to AWS WorkSpaces on the support blogs.
- Work with senior developer to manage large, complex design projects for corporate clients.
- Provide on-call support for critical incident resolution.
- Participate in hiring events, and mentor onboarding candidates.

06/2016 to 03/2018

Sr Systems Engineer – Finance Technology, Amazon Development Center, India

- Work with business team to understand customer issues and will investigate, prototype and deliver new and innovative system solution
- Develop scripts for automation of all aspects of systems rollouts.
- Responsible for designing, writing, testing and deploying code for regional disaster recovery for critical financial forecasting applications on AWS cloud.
- Responsible for monthly windows patching and compliance.
- Responsible for creating and executing change management templates and writing standard operating procedures.
- Responsible for on-premises to AWS cloud migrations of Windows based servers.
- Work with 3rd party vendors and integrate their products into Amazon environment in compliance with Amazon security and deployment standards.
- Provide on-call support for incident critical resolution.

04/2014 to 06/2016

Windows Administrator - Capgemini, Kolkata, India

- L2 Wintel support for a multi-client environment.
- Active Directory maintenance and support.
- Escalated incident support from primary L1 group.
- Change management following standard operating procedures.
- Monthly windows patching and compliance.

11/2013 to 04/2014

CISCO Trainer & Server Administrator – NIIT, Kolkata, India

- Cisco certified network associate trainer.
- Server and NFS administrator.